A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1995-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1995-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
The Library of Virginia
44691
24.05 cubic feet (68 boxes)
Administration, Secretary of
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected information is considered closed for 75 years after date of record creation. Types of records restricted include, but are not limited to: medical information, social security numbers, employee performance reviews, employee grievance materials, and attorney-client privileged documents. Restricted material has been sealed but has not been removed from the collection. Constituent corresponence must be be reviewed for privacy protected information before being used.
Acquisition Information
XX.
Biographical Information
The Office of Administration was established in 1966 as part of the Office of the Governor to assist the Chief Executive in carrying out his duties. Several agencies including the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Building and Planning reported to the Commissioner of Administration. In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governor's top management team or "secretariats," as they are now called. Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments, each headed by a secretary appointed by the Governor. The office of the Secretary of Administration was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed T. Edward Temple, the Commissioner of Administration since 1970, as the first Secretary of Administration. When Temple took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Buildings, Automated Data Processing, Justice and Crime Prevention, State Planning and Community Affairs, Council on the Environment, State Board of Elections and the Office of Special Programs. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since 1972. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature combined the secretariats for administration and finance, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were separated.
The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, is appointed by the governor, and is subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary of Administration oversees general government operations to ensure efficient and effective management of government resources. During Governor Tim Kaine's term, the Secretary of Administration was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over, 8 state agencies and boards as follows: Compensation Board, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Department of Minority Business Enterprises, Public Broadcasting Board, and the State Board of Elections. These agencies mangage the state's real estate portfolio, serve as the state building official, administer employee policies and benefits, oversee procurement, provide laboratory services, promote business opportunities for Small, Women and Minority owned businesses, supervise elections, direct state funds to constitutional officers and public broadcasing entities and safeguard human rights, just to name a few of the important functions handled by agencies under the Secretary of Administration.
Viola O. Baskerville was appointed Secretary of Administration by Governor-elect Timothy Kaine in December 2005. Prior to her appointment, she served on the Richmond City Council starting in 1994 and was elected Vice Mayor by her council peers. In 1997, she was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates for the 71st District, where she served until she relinquished her seat in 2005 to pursue the Democratic nomination for Lieutenant Governor, but was unsuccessful in her bid. Secretary Baskerville received a Bachelor's degree from the College of William and Mary and was awarded a Fulbright Fellowship to study in Germany after graduation. She also earned a law degree from the University of Iowa College of Law. She is native of Richmond, VA and is married to Dr. Archer Baskerville. The couple has two sons, Timothy and Sean.
Kim Farrar and Richard Zorn served at Deputy Secretaries during the Kaine Administration.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, reports, reviews, memorandums, decision briefs, legislative files and other working papers created and collected by the Office of the Secretary of Administration during the gubernatorial term of Virginia Governor Tim Kaine, 2006-2010. This collection consists of 13 records series which document the activities of the Office of the Secretary of Administration, as well as the agencies and boards which fall under its heading.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2002-2010
Series II. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Constituent Correspondence, 2006-2009
Series III. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Secretary of Administration, 2004-2009
Series IV. Decision briefs, 2006-2009
Series V. Environmental impact reports, 2006-2009
Series VI. Intellectual property rights, 2008-2009
Series VII. Legislative files, 2006-2010
Series VIII. Public Broadcasting Board records, 2006-2009
Series IX. Real Property and capital outlay records, 1995-2009
Series X. Special Projects: Civil Rights Memorial, 2006-2009
Series XI. Special Projects: Fort Monroe Federal Area Development Authority (FMFADA), 2006-2009
Series XII. Special Projects: Freedmen's Bureau records, 2006-2009
Series XIII. Special Projects: Higher Education Restructuring, 2006-2009.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2002-2010., Extent: 5.1 cubic feet (15 boxes). (Box 1-15)
  This series is housed in 15 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by agency. These files include correspondence (consituent and internal), along with subject files and supporting materials such as reports and other working papers. Several state agencies operated under the Office of the Secretary of Administration and were referred to as assigned agencies. The assigned agencies of the Office of the Secretary of Administration documented here include the Compensation Board, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, State Board of Elections and the Division of Selected Agency Support Services.
  Notable files include those related to the State Board of Elections and the implementation of the Virginia Election and Registration Information System (VERIS), as well as files pertaining to the Virginia Administrative Dispute Resolution Act (VADRA), which are found in the Dept. of Employment Dispute records. Other significant files include those under the Dept. of Minority Business Enterprise that document issues involved with the Small, Women-owned and Minority Businesses (SWAM) procurement initiative designed to ensure that historically under unitilized business gain access to state contracting opportunities.
  - Compenstation Board, 2006-2008. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Compenstation Board - Fines and Fees Report (FY07), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Compenstation Board - Fines and Fees Report (FY08), 2008. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Compenstation Board - Fines and Fees Report, Exposure Draft (FY08), 2008. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Compenstation Board - Fines and Fees Report, Exposure Draft (FY09), 2009. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Compenstation Board - Jail Cost Report (FY06), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Compenstation Board - Jail Cost Report (FY07), 2008. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Compenstation Board - Jail Cost Report (FY08), 2009. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Compenstation Board - Mental Illness in Jails Report (preliminary), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Compenstation Board - Mental Illness in Jails Report, 2009. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Employment Dispute Resolution, Dept. of, 2006-2009. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Employment Dispute Resolution, Dept. of - Virginia Administrative Dispute Resolution Act (VADRA), 2006. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Employment Dispute Resolution, Dept. of - Virginia Administrative Dispute Resolution Act (VADRA), 2007. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Employment Dispute Resolution, Dept. of - Virginia Administrative Dispute Resolution Act (VADRA), 2009. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Services, Dept. of, 2006 January-August. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Services, Dept. of, 2006 September-December. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Services, Dept. of, 2007. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Services, Dept. of, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Services, Dept. of, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Appraisal training, 2007. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Auditor of Public Accounts Reports on Audit, 2006-2008. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Budget Reduction Impacts, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General Services, Dept. of - eVA fees, 2008. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Services, Dept. of - eVA Sole Source Fee Rebates to Institutions of Higher Education, 2008. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Environmental Laboratories Final Regulations, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Fleet and Fuel Management, 2006-2007. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Green buildings, 2006. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Mail consolidation, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General Services, Dept. of - Patrick Henry Building parking, 2007-2008. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of, 2006. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of, 2007. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of, 2008. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of, 2009. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of, n.d.. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of - Fraud, Waste and Abuse Hotline, 2006-2009. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of - Red Horse airplane crash, 2007-2009. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Human Rights Council, 2006-2009. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 January-April. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 June. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 July 5-14. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 July 17-21. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 August. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 September. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 October. (Box 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2006 November-December; undated. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Email correspondence and weekly reports, 2006. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2007 January-February. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2007 March. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2007 April-June. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2007 July-September. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2007 October-November. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2007 December; undated. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2008 January-March. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2008 April-May. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2008 July. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2008 August. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2008 September-October. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2008; undated. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2009 January-March. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2009 April-June. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2009 July-November. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of, 2009 undated. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Constitutionality of preferences, 2005. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Agency SWAM plans, 2009-2010. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Governor's SWAM Awards, 2007 August-November. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Governor's SWAM Construction Forum, 2006 April 20. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Governor's SWAM Professional Services Forum, 2006 October 4. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Governor's SWAM Professional Services Forum, 2006 October 4. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - SWAM Annual Procurement Plans, 2006 September. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - SWAM Procurement Progress Reports (Public Safety), 2009 August-November. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Virginia Black Expo and SWAM Certification Workshop, 2006 August. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Weekly SWAM Activities Reports (Education Agencies), 2009 August to November. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Weekly SWAM Activities Reports (Education - Colleges and Universities), 2009 August-October. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of - Weekly SWAM Activities Reports (Education - Community Colleges), 2009 August-October. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - State Board of Elections, 2005-2006. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections, 2007 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - State Board of Elections, 2007 August-September. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - State Board of Elections, 2007 October. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections, 2008. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - State Board of Elections, 2009. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - State Board of Elections - Budget FY08, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections - Chesterfield election issues, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - State Board of Elections - Election 2008 binder, 2008 July-August. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - State Board of Elections - Election 2008 binder, 2008 September. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections - Election 2008 binder, 2008 October. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - State Board of Elections - Election 2008 binder, 2008 November-December; undated. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - State Board of Elections - Legislation, 2008-2009. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections - National Change of Address (NCOA) and APA Audit binder, 2006-2008. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - State Board of Elections - National Change of Address (NCOA), 2008. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - State Board of Elections - Reorganization, 2006. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections - Reorganization binder, 2008. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - State Board of Elections - Reports on Audit, 2004-2008. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - State Board of Elections - Voter Turnout and Registration: Background Information, undated. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - State Board of Elections - Voter Turnout and Registration: Comparative Analysis of Key States (draft), 2007 June-July. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - State Board of Elections - SBE binder (part I), 2008. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - State Board of Elections - SBE binder (part II), 2008. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections - SBE binder (part III), 2008. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - State Board of Elections - Wireless Voting, 2007. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS, 2006. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS, 2007. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS, 2008. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS, undated. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Background information binder, 2002-2007. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Complaints from registrars, 2007 May-June. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Help America Vote Act (HAVA), 2006-2009. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: SBE-VERIS binder, 2006 January-September. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Status reports, 2005-2006. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Unisys binder, 2005 September-November. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Unisys binder, 2005 December. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: Unisys binder, 2005 December-2006 January. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - State Board of Elections - VERIS: VERIS Contract, 2005. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Selected Agency Support Services, Division of, 2006-2009. (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Series II. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Constituent Correspondence, 2006-2009., Extent: 1.6 cubic feet (5 boxes). (Box 16-20)
  This series is housed in 5 boxes and is arranged in loose chronological order. This series contains constituent correspondence pertaining to the agencies overseen by the Office of the Secretary of Administration. This series includes correspondence that was originally addressed to Governor Kaine, but were referred to the Secretary of Administration for response on behalf of the Governor, as well as letters addressed directly to the Secretary. Includes incoming correspondence from the general public, as well as from businessmen and civic leaders, college and university officials, and state and federal government officials and legislators, including correspondence from members of the Virginia General Assembly. Also includes some outgoing responses.
  The majority of the correspondence in this series is from 2006 and includes workflow tracking forms from Constituent Services. The 2006 correspondence is arranged by outgoing correspondence number, which corresponds roughly to chronological order. The remainder of the correspondence is in chronological order. Major topics of concern include the proposed demolition of the Eight and Ninth Street office buildings, voting issues (absentee, electronic, voting equipment), state employment issues (compensation, health insurance), and procurement issues (SWAM).
  - Constituent correspondence (2567000-2569999), 2006 February. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Constituent correspondence (2570000-2575999), 2006 February-April. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Constituent correspondence (2576000-1577999), 2006 February-March. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Constituent correspondence (2580000-2589999), 2006 February-April. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Constituent correspondence (2590000-2594999), 2006 April-May. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Constituent correspondence (2595000-2595999), 2006 May. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Constituent correspondence (2596000-2596656), 2006 May-September. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Constituent correspondence (2596660-2596699), 2006 May. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Constituent correspondence (2596700-2596999), 2006 May-July. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Constituent correspondence (2597000-2597999), 2006 May-September. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Constituent correspondence (2598000-2599999), 2006 May-September. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Constituent correspondence (2600000-2601999), 2006 June-September. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Constituent correspondence (2602000-2604999), 2006 June-August. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Constituent correspondence (2605000-2606999), 2006 June-September. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Constituent correspondence (2607000-2610999), 2006 July-August. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Constituent correspondence (2611000-2613999), 2006 August-September. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Constituent correspondence (2614000-2614999), 2006 August-September. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Constituent correspondence (2615000-2615999), 2006 August-September. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Constituent correspondence (2617000-2619999), 2006 September-October. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Constituent correspondence (2620000-2620999), 2006 September-October. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Constituent correspondence (2621000-2621999), 2006 October. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Constituent correspondence (2622000-2622999), 2006 October. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Constituent correspondence (2623000-2623999), 2006 October-November. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Constituent correspondence (2624000-2624999), 2006 October-November. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Constituent correspondence (2625000-2625999), 2006 November. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Constituent correspondence (2626000-2628999), 2006 October-November. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Constituent correspondence (2629000-2631999), 2006 December. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Constituent correspondence (2632000-2633999), 2006 December-2007 January. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2006 January-April. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2006 May-August. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2006 September-December. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 January. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 January. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 February. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 March. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 March. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 March. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 April-August. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 September. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2007 October-December. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2008 January-July. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2008 August-December. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2009 January-June. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2009 July-December. (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Series III. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Office of the Secretary, 2004-2009., Extent: 2 cubic feet (6 boxes). (Box 21-26)
  This series is housed in 6 boxes and includes incoming and outgoing correspondence of the Secretary of Administration Viola Baskerville, as well as subject files. Correspondence files are arranged chronologically and subject files are arranged alphabetically. The majority of the correspondence is this series is from other Cabinet Secretaries, but this series also contains correspondence from the Governor's Chief of Staff, and state boards and agencies, including the Office of the Attorney General. The subject files accumulated by the Secretary of Administration document budget reductions, the federal stimulus, and other matters with which the Secretary was involved.
  - Correspondence, 2006 February-April. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2006 May-December. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2007 January-December. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2009 January-2010 January. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Advance Auto Parts, 2009. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - African American Advisory Counil, 2005-2006. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - ARC of Virginia v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 2009. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Audit reports, 2005. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Audit reports, 2007. (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Audit reports, 2008-2009. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Blue Book, 2009. (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Budget, 2006-2008. (Box 22, Folder 5)